以下内容提供
the following content is provided under
CreativeCommons许可您的支持
a Creative Commons license your support
将帮助MITOpenCourseWare继续
will help MIT OpenCourseWare continue to
提供高质量的教育资源
offer high quality educational resources
免费
for free
捐款或查看额外的捐款
to make a donation or to view additional
数百个麻省理工学院课程的材料
materials from hundreds of MIT courses
访问位于ocw.mit.edu的麻省理工学院开放式课件
visit MIT opencourseware at ocw.mit.edu
好吧，有三件事要提一个
well so three things to mention one was
你还记得我上次列出的一份清单
you remember last time I made a list of
六七种不同的情况
six or seven different situations where
他们X等于B和可能的问题
they X equal B and problems that could
出现上一次是当只是
arise the last one was when a was just
方式太大，不适合核心，但在
way too big to fit into core but in the
中间是那么其他的其他方法
middle were other methods so other
像列一样的问题
issues like columns being nearly
当克斯施密特出现时依赖
dependent when gram-schmidt will come up
首先，我想说我知道那里
first I want to say that I know there
在这两个页面II思想错别字
are typos in the two pages I I thought
你可能只想看到它
you might just like to see the very
书的两页初稿所以
first draft of two pages of the book so
人们有时会问我多长时间？
people sometimes ask me how long does
这本书采取写，所以我开始时
the book take to write so I started when
1806年五年开始，所以我进入
1806 five started a year ago so I'm into
第二年通常需要两年
the second year and it usually takes two
年，系统是我手工编写的
years and the system is I write by hand
所以我写了那些你打开的页面
so I wrote those opening pages that you
手工看了两页然后我扫描了它们
saw two pages by hand then I scan them
到孟买我最好的朋友
to Mumbai where my best friend in the
世界
world
用拼写错误输入他们没问题因为
types them with typos no problem because
我要让这么多的变化，一个
I'm gonna make so many changes that a
几个错别字是反正没事，所以他扫描
few typos are nothing anyway so he scans
他们回到我打字然后我开始
them back to me typed and then I start
如果我很幸运并有了改变，那就做出改变
making changes if I'm lucky and have the
我在这里谈论它的机会
chance to talk about it in here then I
实现更好的事情，我扫描
realize better things to do and I scan
回到他身边然后回到我身边
back to him and back to me and back to
他回到我身边那就是那个地方
him and back to me so that's where that
无论如何我两年都消失了
two years disappear anyway I'm quite
在我开始之前对这两页感到高兴
happy with those two pages until I start
改善它们还有另一个话题
improving them okay and one other topic
从过去我认为是那样的
from the past that I thought was that
在课堂上出来的不在笔记中
came out in class wasn't in the notes
但你还记得那一天吗？
yet do you remember the day that we
最小化
minimized
不同的规范
different norm
l1或l2或maxL无穷大范数
l1 or l2 or max L infinity norm for with
解决问题的条件
the condition of solving with a
约束这个方程
constraint that this equation was
我很满意我在2d能够画出一个
satisfied I'm in 2d to be able to draw a
图片和约束是一行
picture and the constraint is one line
这就是线条看起来的样子
and that's about what the line looks
像这样我会再次提请这里这么
like so I'm gonna draw here again so
我正在做的是放一些数字
what I'm doing is putting some numbers
在以这种洞察力，我画了一个左右
in to that insight that I drew about a
一周前你还记得那个，因为我
week ago do you remember that because I
以为这真的说明了为什么如何
thought that really illustrates why how
L1和L2以及L无穷大是不同的
L 1 and L 2 and L infinity are different
让我让我在这里画出L21
let's let me draw the L 2 1 here so
哪来的这条线，因此X点
where's the point on this line so the X
必须躺在这条线上，在哪里
has to lie on this line and where is the
具有最小总和的点
point that has the smallest sum of
正方形标准L2范数如此
squares norm standard L 2 norm so
几何上哪个点好
geometrically where is that point well
什么是具有规范的点集
what does the set of points with norm
一个看起来像L2它是一个圆圈
one look like for L 2 it's a circle
是的，所以我们只是把那个圈子吹了起来
right so we just blow that circle up or
缩小它直到触及它
shrink it down until it touches this
事情，现在它会触及它的位置
thing and now it'll touch where it
接触它会触及我们的半径
touches it'll touch where our radius is
垂直所以有圆圈
perpendicular so there's the circle
L2中有我们最好的一点，因为如果
there's our best point in L 2 because if
因为如果我们选择另一个点，我们就会
because if we picked another point we'd
有吹的规范，即规范会
have to blow the norm that norm would
必须更大才能完成
have to be bigger to go through that
这点显然是第一个
point so that's clearly the first one
实际上我们可以看到
and and actually we can probably see
它是什么，因为如果我们知道的话
what it is because those if we know
那些是垂直的，我知道斜率
those are perpendicular I know the slope
这条线所以我认为是斜坡
of this line so I think that the slope
这条线就像是3/4
of this line is something like 3/4
可能来自那里或者可能是4/3
probably coming from there or maybe 4/3
我能算出来，我认为是的
I can we'll figure it out I think it's
三分之三是的，我想我会找到的
four thirds yeah I think that I'll find
那一点是最有趣的一点
that point then the most interesting one
是l1规范，因为是什么
was the l1 norm because what was the
单位球的形状为l1a钻石
shape of the unit ball for l1 a diamond
对钻石那么钻石那么
right a diamond so the diamond that
第一接触线在这里，真实
first touches the line is here that's
获胜点，如果线是3X.
the winning point and if the line is 3 X
1加4X2等于1然后我知道
1 plus 4 X 2 equal 1 then I know that
那一点是XX1将是0和X2
that point is X X 1 will be 0 and X 2
将是1/4，这是胜利点
will be 1/4 so that's the winning point
在l1，我想我计算了这个
in l1 and I think I calculated this
这是l2的胜利点
right that's a winning point in l2
我想会让我们看到这种情况发生了变化
I think will be let's see this goes up
对我来说，我想是这么想的
to I I'm so moving down the line I think
这将有三个二十五分之一
this would have three twenty fifths for
二十五分之二，我不会停下来
twenty fifths I won't stop to derive
这一点，但至少现在这是的，这
that but at least now this yeah that
斜坡看起来像4/3上升为
slope is looking like 4/3 goes up for
当它穿过三个那四个和
when it crosses three and that four and
三个人当然是从那里来的
the three came from there and of course
你注意到我选择了我已经缩放了
you notice I've chosen that I've scaled
它适合行3米乘3
it to fit the line three times three
2015年3月9日第25届五分之一
fifths in 3 2015 9 25th
加上162525th是1，最后是什么
Plus 16 25th 25th is 1 and finally what
关于L无限是什么画面
about L infinity what was the picture
那里的单位球是什么样的
there what's the unit ball look like in
最大标准为2d，右边是正方形
2d for the max norm it's a square right
因此广场将击中这两个
so the square will hit there these two
在广场上，这是一个45度
on the square are this is a 45-degree
现在在那个广场上划线它
line now on that square it hits it at
那个尖点等x1和
that sharp point and so the x1 and the
x2是平等的，我认为它们是
x2 are equal and I think they're
大概
probably
如果我们的话，让我们看看他们是否平等
let's see if they're equal if me if we
使它们成为1/7
made them 1/7 that would be
然后我有三个七分加四分
then I have three sevenths plus four
sevens等于7/7是的我想我们做的
sevens equals 7/7 yeah I think we make
那么一点七七七
some one seventh one seventh then so
这将是X无穷远点3/7
that would be the X infinity point 3/7
再加上4/7给出一个，为什么我要提到
plus 4/7 gives one so why do I mention
这首先是因为我之前做过的
this first because when I did it before
我没有真的扔过照片
I just threw pictures without really
解决问题，其次是因为
solving the problem and secondly because
在思考这个项目的未来
in thinking of ahead about projects this
是我想要的那种项目
is the kind of project that I would
觉得挺有意思的明显
think is quite interesting obviously as
这是P等于1这是P等于
this is P equal 1 this is P equal to
这是P等于无穷大，我猜
this is P equal infinity and I guess
从图片中可以清楚地看到
it's pretty clear from the pictures that
随着P的增加，这一点开始于此
as P increases this point starts up here
和向下移动一行，并在这里结束了
and moves down the line and ends up here
而且我不知道该怎样移动
and I have no idea like what to move
什么解决方案是一个不同的P
what the solution is for a different P
以及如何移动并使其成功
and how it moves and to make it make it
更多关于项目在3d中发生的事情
more about project what happens in 3d
如果我有一个在3d中3d中会发生什么
what happens in 3d in 3d if I have one
在3d中的方程然后我有一个平面和
equation in 3d then I have a plane and
这些将成为3D钻石
these this would become a diamond a 3d
钻石这将是一个3d球体
diamond this would be a 3d sphere this
将是一个他们将扩展到的3d立方体
would be a 3d cube they would expand to
打那架飞机，我不知道有多少
hit that plane and I don't know how many
在这种情况下，你会得到零
zeroes you get in that case so that
将是一个等式的情况
would be the case of one one equation so
这架钻石有一架飞机
there'd be a plane that these diamond
Q的球体和Q扩展直到它们击中
Q's sphere and Q expand until they hit
它或你可以有两个约束二
it or you could have two constraints two
方程所以，如果我们有两个方程和
equations so if we had two equations and
三个未知数将成为一条线
three unknowns that would be a line
再次，但我们会得到多少零
again but would we get how many zeroes
我们会遇到这些不同的情况吗？
would we get in these different cases
我是多么稀疏l1会好起来的
how sparse is l1 gonna be okay can I
只是像的夺回我们
just that's like a recapture of what we
我觉得这很好吗？
did I thought it was a it's nice
偶尔
occasionally
有图片展示什么什么
have pictures showing what what a
解决方案现在是我的解决方案
solution where the solution is now I'm
来到当天的主题
coming to the to the topic of the day
这是克施密特等等
which is gram-schmidt and so
克-施密特第一是标准
gram-schmidt number one is the standard
将在1806年教授的方式和
way that would be taught in 1806 and the
结果是什么克斯施密特
result is so what's gram-schmidt about
我会在这里放下一般性的
and I'll just put down here general
克-施密特的事实我们从一开始
facts of gram-schmidt we start with a
矩阵a它有n列，但它们是
matrix a it's got n columns but they're
不正交，事实上它们可能是
not orthogonal and in fact they may be
条件严格的列可能是
badly conditioned columns might be
几乎依赖于别人我要
nearly dependent on the others I'm gonna
假设列是独立的但是
assume the columns are independent but
他们可能几乎没有独立
they might be barely independent so
克施密特所以他们就是那些线
gram-schmidt so they're those lines then
会有点像指点
would be sort of like pointing very
几乎平行，但克施密特打开了
nearly parallel but gram-schmidt opens
上图得到一个矩阵qan
up the picture to get a matrix q an
具有列Q1至Q的正交矩阵
orthogonal matrix with columns Q 1 to Q
n是正交的，所以它得到了一个
n which are orthonormal so it gets a
Q的完美基础，这就是什么
perfect basis of Q's and so that's what
克施密特做的就是这些
gram-schmidt does and these are
以不同的方式做不同的方式
different ways to do it different ways
我真的要组织计算
to organize the computation I really
只把标准的方式放在什么地方
only put the standard way in what is
这个神秘的RI声称，所以他们
this mysterious R I claim that so they
来这些Q的是
come these these the Q's are
A的组合所以有一些
combinations of the A's so there's some
矩阵告诉我那些是什么
matrix to tell me what those
组合是或如果我回去
combinations are or if I go back go
倒退，并说A好
backwards and say well the A's are
Q的组合就是我的意思
combinations of the Q's that's what I'm
关于做，如果我说的每一个是一个
about to do if I say each a is a
Q的组合意味着我的一个
combination of Q's that means that my a
可以
may
Trix是我的Q矩阵时间，有些是矩阵
Trix is my Q matrix time some are matrix
这告诉我组合正确
which tells me the combinations right
当我乘以右边的R时，我就是
when I multiply by R on the right I'm
采用Q列的组合
taking combinations of the columns of Q
并得到一个如此公正的列
and getting the columns of a so just
像Lu一样，你可以继续前进
like Lu it's kind of you go forward with
我们去的算法到达你这里
the algorithm to reach you here we go
用算法转发到达Q.
forward with the algorithm to reach Q
但是当我们想了解put时
but then when we want to understand put
它把它在一个简单的公式就
it put it in one simple equation it
事实证明最好去
turns out to be like better to go
向后说，原来是怎么回事
backwards and say how is the original a
与最终的Q有关，必须有
related to the final Q and there has to
当我说话的时候我总觉得有些好
be some R ok I always feel when I talk
关于克施密特，我通常以
about gram-schmidt I usually end with
相当于QR，当然还有MATLAB
that equal Q R and of course the MATLAB
在MATLAB中命令正好是QR
command is exactly Q R so in MATLAB
你问的命令是Q
you're asking for the command would be Q
R的一个而不是一个如此的Lu
R of a instead of Lu of a so it would
给你一个Q和R这就是MATLAB
give you a Q and R that's what MATLAB
现在将输出，因为我说Q是事情
will output now as I say Q is the thing
我们正在构建R是组合
we're constructing R is the combinations
我们需要得到我们想要的东西
that we need to get what we want and so
这是一个有点它是在结束
it's a little it comes at the end
什么是R，但实际上R是
what the heck was R but actually R is
真是一个简单的想法，所以我想展示
really a simple idea so I want to show
在开始而不是结束
that at the beginning instead of the end
好的，所以我打算把Q移到这里
okay so I'm going to move Q over here as
Q反向但Q反Q是什么
Q inverse but what is Q inverse Q
转换正确因为我创造了一个
transpose right because I've created an
正交矩阵所以这个神秘的R
orthogonal matrix so this mysterious R
是Q转置一个让我放
is Q transpose a and let me just put
让我有点让它成长
here the let me sort of make it grow out
进入具有Q的矩阵
into matrices that has the Q's along the
行Q转换当然是QN转置
rows Q transpose of course QN transpose
Q1我只是转置
Q 1 transpose I just
我正在将矩阵转置到它上面
I'm transposing the matrix above it so
这些列成为A的行数
these columns become rows times the A's
a1到nn什么是典型的条目
a 1 to a n so what is a typical entry in
我们这就是我想说的原因
our that's really why I want to say
你能做到这一点并不神秘
nothing mysterious about this you can
看看你最终的结果是对的
see what you end up with it'll be right
在我们面前这是什么典型的
in front of us here what is a typical
第I行J列中的条目是什么
what is the entry in row I column J of
我们确定这就是所有这些
our ok this this says that all those
我们的Qi中的条目转置时间AJ
entries in our our Qi transpose times AJ
对，这是繁殖的旧方式
right that's the old way to multiply
矩阵和它是最好的方法
matrices and on it's the best way for
换句话说，这一行乘以一列
this a row times a column in other words
我们的只是内在的产品
the ours are just the inner product the
Q的第8个积分
dot product of the Q's with the 8th of
Q与A的那就是那种
the Q's with the A's that's that's sort
对我们来说并不神秘
of like nothing mysterious about our
因为Q是我们的正交矩阵
because Q is an orthogonal matrix we
能够把它放在这里
were able to put it over here
得到一个很好的表达R，看看是什么
get a nice expression for R and see what
这真的是你能做到的好
it really is so are you good you can do
在最后或在路线上，但它是
are at the end or on the route but it's
只是Q的内在产品
just the inner product of the Q's with
A现在好了，克我施密特可以
the A's ok now what's gram-schmidt can I
我有点想你已经看过了
I'm sort of thinking you've seen the
克-施密特的基本思想，但让我们来
basic ideas of gram-schmidt but let's
回顾所以我从一开始就是这样开始的
review so I start with I start with a so
什么是克施密特从1开始
what does gram-schmidt begin with a 1 it
取第一列所以这些是z'
takes that first column so so these a z'
一般不是正交但是
are not orthogonal generally but the
第一个方向没问题
first direction is okay
我对第一个没有任何抱怨
I have no complaints about the first
方向，除了一个可能不是
direction except that a one might not be
一个单位向量，所以q1只是一个
a unit vector so q1 will just be a one
在其范数有一个单位矢量的
over its norm to have a unit vector the
克-施密特的整个想法是在q2中
whole idea of gram-schmidt is in q2 so
什么是q2整个想法来到这里
what is q2 the whole idea is coming here
是的，这是你唯一需要的东西
yeah it's the only thing you need to
知道，图片显示它如此q2我
know and the picture shows it so q2 I
从a开始-但它不是正交的
start with a - but it's not orthogonal
到a-1
to a-1
所以我该怎么做才能弄清楚
so what do I do I figure out the
在一个a2的一个队列的部件
component of a queue of a2 in the a one
方向和我删除它，所以我采取这一
direction and I remove it so I take that
矢量路程，我留下了这
vector away and I'm left with this
矢量所以有一个我会打电话的矢量
vector so there is a vector I'll call
a2所以a2是原来的小a2
that a 2 so a2 is the original little a2
与一个单向除去，从而A2
with the a One Direction removed so a2
像这样什么有什么公式
is like so what what's the formula for
我刚刚做的就是关键的洞
what I just did this is the hole the key
那克克施密特重复的步骤
step that that gram-schmidt repeats over
一遍又一遍，这是真的
and over and over again it's truly
无聊
boring
好了，所以它减去记得非常清楚
okay so it subtracts well remember that
这与q1和q1的方向相同
this is the same direction as q1 and
最好使用q1，因为
it's better to work with q1 because
我们发现那个人我们已经得到了它和我们
we've found that guy we've got it and we
知道我们知道这是一个单位向量
know we know it's a unit vector so
这是我的线性代数问题是什么
here's my linear algebra question what's
我想要的2的组成部分
the component of a 2 that I want to
减去其中的组件
subtract off its the component in the
Q1的方向就是这个
direction of Q 1 it's this in the
Q1的方向让我公正
direction of Q 1 and let me just
记得
remember
很明显，这个角度正在形成
so obviously that angle is coming into
所以这将是一个2转置Q1
it so that'll be an a 2 transpose Q 1
时间Q1就是这样
times Q 1 that's it
这是我们删除的组件
that's the component that we removed
也许我也许我更愿意把它写成
maybe I maybe I'd prefer to write it as
q1转置a-我不知道
q1 transpose a - I don't know
管点当然没关系
doesn't matter of course the tube dot
产品在那里说也许我会
products are there saying maybe I will
只是，是的，现在好了，是什么
just yeah yeah well okay now what is
应该做什么做到这一点
supposed to what does what does that
矢量应该实现它的假设
vector supposed to achieve it's supposed
作为这个向量这是这个向量
to be this vector this is this vector
我真打算叫两个因为
I'm really going to call a two because
它正朝着q2的正确方向发展
it's on in the right direction for q2
但它还不正常，那么q2是什么
but it is not yet normal so what is q2
那么我就说这个家伙得到了
then so I'm saying this guy got the
方向对这个东西减去了
direction right this thing subtracted
这个向量得到了正确的方向
off this vector got that direction right
它得到了它-现在是什么q2我
it got it as a - what is q2 now that I
想要完成我有方向
want to finish I've got the direction
我想做的就是让它成为一个单位
all I want to do is get it to be a unit
矢量，所以我只需要2
vector so I just take a 2 over its
正常，双步是整体
normal that double step is the whole
整个事情在克施密特的事情
thing in gram-schmidt the whole thing
减去关中的组件
subtract off the components in the
方向已经设定，你得到
directions already set and you get
一些全新的方向
something in a totally new direction
称为资本A然后你分裂
called a capital A and then you divide
通过它的长度使它成为一个单位向量
by its length to make it a unit vector
这给你新的Q所以你看
and that gives you the new Q so you see
只是为了表明我们已经明白了
just to show that we've got the point
那么针对q3的下一步呢？
what about the next step aiming for q3
所以告诉我3我应该是3
so tell me what a 3 should be a 3 I'm
从这开始，我要去
gonna start with this and I'm going to
减去一些东西我要去的东西
subtract off some stuff what am I going
减去
to subtract off
是组件III转置右x
is the component III transpose right x
q1q1我还没检查那个
q1 q1 and I didn't yet check that that
这使得这与正交
makes that this came out orthogonal to
Q1我会回来的，现在我有我
q1 I'll come back to that now I have I
我做了我应该做的一切吗？
have I done everything I should do here
有三个没有，我还有一步
with a three no I've got one more step
采取，我应该采取这两个步骤
to take and I should take the two steps
分别
separately
它被称为修改过的gram-schmidt和
it's called modified gram-schmidt and
我想做的是减去q2
what I want to do is subtract off the q2
组件那么q2的多重做什么
component so what what multiple of q2 do
我需要因为q2已被设置
I need to because q2 has been set by the
时间我到了a3所以这里发生了什么
time I get to a3 so what what goes here
a3转置Q2谢谢你，如果
a3 transpose Q 2 thanks thanks you if
你看一个代码说一个MATLAB代码
you look at a code say a MATLAB code to
做克施密特哦最后的q3是什么
do gram-schmidt Oh what's the final q3
然后将其标准化，以便你拿3个
then normalize it so you take a 3 which
是在正确的方向，你分裂
is in the right direction and you divide
通过它的长度得到一个单位向量是啊
by its length to get a unit vector yeah
让我回来写一下
let me just come back and write and
重新检查我做得对，我得到了
recheck that I did it right that I got
正确的方向所以我的意思是什么
the right direction so what do I mean by
正确的方向我应该拥有什么
the right direction what should I have
我该怎么检查那个人我
what should I check about that guy I
应检查其内积
should check that its inner product with
q1如果这是正确的方向
q1 is it if this is the right direction
走那条路然后我应该检查一下
to go that way then I should check I
我希望能得到它
have to check hopefully I got the
正确的公式，它是点积
formula right that it's dot product
Q1的内积为0
inner product with Q 1 is 0
谢谢你，让我这样吧
thank you so let me just so is it
很明显它是内心的
obvious that it is take the inner
与之相关的点积的产物
product of the dot product of that with
你能得到什么？
q1 what do you get you get
你得到相同的数字Q1a2
you get the same number Q 1 a 2
转置Q1你得到那个数字和
transpose Q 1 you get that number and
在这里你得到一个Q1转置
over here you're getting a Q 1 transpose
Q1用Q1换位，所以我看到了
Q 1 transpose with Q 1 so I'm you see
我正在做什么和Bobby看起来像
what I'm doing and Bobby it looks like
我检查那个Q本来会更好
it would have been better I check that Q
1转置2是0是啊它是Q1
1 transpose a 2 is 0 yeah it is Q 1
在这里转置2Q1转置2或
transpose a 2 here Q 1 transpose a 2 or
a2转置Q1我不介意和我
a 2 transpose Q 1 I don't mind and I
在这里有另一个Q1转置Q1
have another Q 1 transpose Q 1 here and
那是什么什么是Q1转的Q1
what is that what is Q 1 transpose Q 1
它是1所以检查
it is 1 so check
好吧那是克-施密特标准拉姆
okay that's gram-schmidt standard Ram
你之前见过的Smit我是
Smit which you have met before now I'm
准备好更好的克施密特你
ready for a better gram-schmidt you
可以说我是更好的克施密特
could say I'm better gram-schmidt
因为这里有啥这将是
because here so what's it going to be
差异在这里，我拿了A的
the difference here I took the A's in
他们原来的订单现在假设我做了
their original order now suppose I did
消除消除
that with elimination elimination
通常我们这样写作为行
usually we write as acting on the row so
所以考虑消除我所看到的
so thinking of elimination I'm seeing in
行将是什么危险
the rows what would be the danger in
采取行顺序不做行
taking the rows in order doing no row
交流只是弄清楚每一个角度
exchanges just figure out the pivot each
时间并杀死列的其余部分
time and kill the rest of the column and
然后继续往下走
then move on so taking the rows in the
命令他们来到任何可能的地方
order they came whatever it might be
什么是风险，为什么会这样
what's the risk and what why would
MATLAB没有这样做，因为有些东西可以
MATLAB not do that because something can
非常小，完全炸毁你的
be very small and totally blow up your
计算，那是枢轴数
calculation and that's that pivot number
有问题的是你知道a2
sort of the question is you know if a2
非常靠近一个，所以让我画一个新的
is very near a one so let me draw a new
图片所以这是a1的风险
picture so here's the risk so a1 was
无论如何2真的很接近
whatever it was if a 2 is really close
相同的方向，然后我
to the same direction then I'm
减去几乎所有的和
subtracting off almost all of it and
我有一些小小的东西
I've got some tiny little bit for the
像枢轴一样的新方向
new direction that's like the pivot in
消除它的数量
elimination it's the number that sort of
测量什么是新的什么是新的行和
measures what's new what's a new row and
淘汰或新的专栏
elimination or the new column in
克施密特给你，如果是的话
gram-schmidt gives you and if that's too
小我的意思是在淘汰我们
small I mean like in elimination we
我会说我们永远不会使用
would as I say we would never use an
消除一般矩阵的代码
elimination code on a general matrix
没有检查枢轴的大小
that didn't check the size of the pivot
和交换行，必要时也
and exchange rows when necessary well
与gram-schmidt类似，它可以采取
similarly with gram-schmidt it can take
那些列是为了那个
those columns in order that's the
标准克-施密特参加专栏
standard gram-schmidt taking the columns
按顺序，但只有每次检查
in order but only if it checks each time
那一点点好一点
that a little bit that a little bit well
在新的部分将是什么
that the in the new part what would be
新的部分是足够大的能够
the new part is is big enough to be able
以我们的东西，如果分
to we have to divide by the thing and if
即A2是微小的是一个很小的载体，这是
that a2 is tiny is a tiny vector this is
除以2和之后是
dividing by a 2 and and onwards is
建立在我们不能的舍入错误
building in roundoff error that we can't
再次删除它是我们坚持它所以
remove again it's we're stuck with it so
这是列交换列
that's the column exchange column
转发想法更多
pivoting idea in a sort of a more
专业的克施密特，它需要
professional gram-schmidt and it needs
这样做我必须能够检查
to do it so i have to be able to check
比较这一点，如果它
compare this this little bit if it is
什么我会去做什么
little with what what am I going to
与淘汰相比我看了
compare with in elimination I looked
在列的其余部分为更大的
down the rest of the column for a bigger
在这里，我想知道我猜是什么
number here I want to know I guess what
我要做的是我必须找到这个
I have to do is I have to find this this
组件不仅来自a2而且来自所有
component not just from a2 but from all
剩下的A和我会选择
the remaining A's and I'll pick the
最大的就是那句话我
biggest so there in in that sentence I
说列交换的主要思想
said the main idea of column exchanges
一旦你获得Q1一套是
is once you get q1 set which was
肯定q1是最简单的一个
certainly q1 was the easiest one in the
世界，但也许甚至q1哦我猜
world but maybe even for q1 oh I guess
它甚至可能发生
it could even happen
你喜欢那样的开始
you like that would be starting like
从左上角的a0开始
starting with a0 up in the upper left
消失的角落就像是什么样的
corner for elimination like like what a
如果a1如果我的话，在这里开始新的一天
way to start the day here if a1 if my
矩阵a有一个小小的a1然后我
matrix a had a tiny little a1 then I
应该寻找更大的一个来获得
should look for a bigger one to get the
第一个Q选择让我们假设给予
very first Q chosen let's suppose give
我们这里有一个合理的机会
ourselves a reasonable chance here let's
假设一个是一个体面的大小所以
suppose a one was a decent size so so as
我已经画了，但是2可能不是或者
I've drawn then but a 2 might not or the
下一步可能不是，如果我使用2作为我
next step might not be if I use a 2 as I
说它可能与a1方向相同
say it could be same direction as a1
几乎然后我正在与之合作
virtually and then I'm just working with
那个小小的东西是什么呢
that little piece so what's the what do
我必须做不同的我必须
I have to do differently I have to be
能够比较这个小块
able to compare this little piece with
所有其他的潜在可能性，所以
all the other potential possibilities so
所以，让我写下你的所作所为
so let me just write down what you have
你必须做一个与众不同的事情
to do you have to do in a different
订单所以现在这是列
order so this is now with column
枢轴柱交换柱旋转
pivoting column exchange column pivoting
允许或尽可能
allowed or as possible
所以我必须找到它
so to make it possible I have to find
不仅仅是一件小Q的
not only a to the piece of Q of little a
-我必须找到一件我刚才的作品
- I have to find a to the piece I'm just
要复制我必须拿第二个
gonna copy that I have to take my second
列减去q1部分和那个
column subtract off the q1 part and that
可能很小所以我必须比较它
could be small so I have to compare it
同
with
哦，我没有，我没有写这个页面
oh I haven't I haven't written this page
所以我没有想到一个符号
up so I haven't got a notation in mind
然而
yet
让我，我不会，我不会给它一个名字我
let me I won't I won't give it a name I
还必须在此步骤之前计算
have to also compute at this step before
在决定q2之前决定这是非
deciding before deciding q2 this is non
描述如何决定q2如何
describing how do how to decide q2 the
第二矢量和我说，
second vector and I'm saying that the
决定q2的方法不仅仅是看
way to decide q2 is not only to look not
只有采取计件的A2也
only to take the piece of a2 but also
在这片作品A3的外观和
the piece of a3 look at this piece and
看看所有其他作品
look at all the other pieces
现在我的政策标准是什么
and now what will be my policy standard
克施密特接受了这个和
gram-schmidt accepted this one and
没看这些，但现在我要去了
didn't look at these but now I'm gonna
看看他们所有，我会采取的
look at them all and I'm gonna take the
最大的我要拿最大的
largest I'm gonna take the largest and
这将是我想要的2想法
that will be a 2 thought I want so it
如果这个人是，那可能不是这个
might not be this one if this guy is
最大的我先是第3列
largest then I'm taking column 3 first
这将是我的a2，然后我会说
and that will be my a2 and then I'll say
细，然后Q2将是这一点，A2
fine and then Q 2 will be this that a2
在它的正常情况下你会看到差异
over its normal you see the difference
它并不令人兴奋，你可能会想到
it's not exciting and you might think
等一下，这是一个很大的问题
wait a minute this is a heck of a lot
更多的工作，但事实并非如此
more work but it isn't it isn't actually
更多的工作，因为这些都是
more work because these are all the
那些看起来像我们的东西
things these ones that look like we're
付出代价，我们正在计算所有这些
paying a price we're computing all these
替代方案，但我们必须这样做
alternatives but we had to do that
最后无论如何你看到了让我
eventually anyway do you see that let me
再说一遍这个标准
say it again and and that the standard
办法把所有的组件，如用于
way took all the components like for
这里有标准的方式等到你有了
here a standard way waited until you got
到第3列然后减去它
to column 3 and then subtract it off
两件作品等到你到达
both pieces waited until you got to
第4栏减去了三件
column 4 subtracted off three pieces
这样你就减掉了
this way you're subtracting off the
一旦你知道它是什么，第一件
first piece as soon as you know what it
一旦你知道q1你就应该
should be as soon as you know q1 you
从所有剩余的向量中删除它
remove it from all the remaining vectors
而且你希望看到最大的东西
and you look to sees what's the biggest
你选择我说过的最大的一个
you pick the biggest one I said maybe
是这个人所以你移动那个
it's this guy so you move that one
你是一些排列矩阵
you're some permutation matrix is going
将它移动到第二列看到它
to move it to the second column see it
从第三栏开始，但我是
started in the third column but I'm
要把它移到第二个，因为它是
gonna move it to the second because it's
最重要的是我做对了
the biggest then I do the right thing I
发现Q2现在我去
find q2 and now I go on
-先生
- sir
第三个急性或朝向q3以及如何
the third acute or toward q3 and how
我会找到q3，我会说橄榄我
will I find q3 it'll be I'll say olive I
想要挑选最大的专栏
want to pick the biggest column to work
所以我减去了q2组件
with so I subtract off the q2 components
这很容易说，但我从来没有
this is like easy to say but I had never
喜欢弄清楚之前让我来
liked figured it out before so let me
再说一遍然后我会离开
just say it again and then I'll leave
和你在一起我如何获得q3
that with you how do I get q3 I've got
我已修复了他们碰巧的两列
I've fixed two columns they happen to be
也许不一定是前两个但是
maybe not necessarily the first two but
两列两个队列设置，我是
two columns two queues are set and I'm
寻找下一个好吧，我继续
looking for the next one okay I go on
我看看剩下的所有专栏
and I look at all the remaining columns
所有这些都被减去了
all of which have had subtracted off
他们的q1和q2部分
their q1 and q2 parts
所以我与q1正交
so I've orthogonalize with respect to q1
和q2我看剩下的所有
and q2 I look at all the remaining
我必须与之合作并挑选的东西
things that I have to work with and pick
最大的就像挑选一样
the biggest just like picking the
进入枢轴的最大数量还可以
biggest number to go into the pivot okay
那就是我不认为我能说出来
that's that's I don't think I can say it
不再重复自己了
any more without just repeating myself
我把它带到课堂上，因为我
and I bring it here into class because I
我没有意识到这一点
had not sort of appreciated the point
没有额外的工作涉及到你
that that no extra work was involved you
刚做了这些减法
just did these subtraction off
所有剩余的减法
subtractions for all the remaining
你开始之前的一列
columns of a before you start on the
接下来的工作是好的
next job is that okay
最后这些笔记将描述这一点
eventually the notes will describe that
也许他们甚至做是的，我认为他们
maybe they even do yeah I think they
即使我写了它，但我没有
even do I wrote it but I didn't
现在明白了
understand it now
一点点改善没关系，是的，是的，是的
little improvement okay so yes yeah yeah
只有我们不称他们为枢纽或我们
only we don't call them pivots or we
应该也许我们应该，我不知道是什么
should maybe we should I don't know what
word用来获得最大的专栏
word is used to get the biggest column
其余
remaining
什么，是的，是的，是的
or something yeah yeah yeah each time
对吧，只是你知道是否列
right it's just you know if the columns
是在一个愚蠢的为了这使他们在
were in a stupid order this puts them in
正确的订单好吧终于来了
the right order okay finally come these
奇怪的名字叫喊俄罗斯没有
weird names cried off Russian are no the
实际上我不知道他不是我
actually I don't know what he isn't I
不应该承认在磁带上如此
shouldn't admit that on the tape so
那是什么意思
what's the what's the idea there so
再次，我们正在解决斧等于B上这
again we're solving ax equal B so this
什么是真的会被哭掉
is gonna be cried off what's what was
他的想法很好，我想解决斧头等于B
his idea well I want to solve ax equal B
a当然是一个非常大的矩阵我
a is a big matrix pretty big of course I
不打算反其道而行，将是
don't plan to invert it that would be
疯狂的我用大矩阵做什么a
insane what I can do with a big matrix a
特别是如果它很稀疏的话
especially if it's sparse which made it
使这将是一个大型稀疏一
so that that would be a large sparse a
会是一件好事会很好
would be a good would be a good
候选人克雷洛夫所以它是什么，
candidate for Krylov so what is it that
你可以用一个大的便宜和快速的我
you can do cheap and fast with a large I
意思是真的很大，但真的很稀疏
mean really large but really sparse
矩阵a你可以做矩阵乘以a
matrix a you can do a matrix times a
矢量，这是我们的矩阵，有
vector and here's our matrix and there's
我们的载体所以或者是的，我们可以开始
our vector so or yeah we could start
使用向量B，我们可以乘以一次
with a vector B we can multiply a times
B我们可以乘以B和B倍
B we can multiply a times a times B and
当然，我这样写，我从来没有
of course I write it that way I never I
从来没有我的意思，如果你乘以aa
never I mean like if you multiply a a
第一次，然后就像你知道的那样
times a first then like you know
转到你的MATLAB账户吧
turn in your MATLAB account you just
必须这样做的
have to do it that way
好吧，然后你继续下去，其中
okay and then you keep going which of
当然这是一个平方B但你没有
course that's a squared B but you didn't
形成在一个平方，然后就高达
form a squared and then on up to in the
结束你得到一些说KK
end you get to some a to the say K K
减一
minus one
当然，这是计算为a
be but of course that's computed as a
是前一个八次的时间
times the previous one which was eight
是前一次的，所以有一个
times the previous one so there is a
束，其很可能是载体的
bunch of vectors which are likely to be
独立，所以他们跨越空间
independent that so they span a space
它被称为Krylov空间
and it's called the Krylov space so
这些跨度是他们的组合
there's these span they're combinations
组合
combinations
给，给
give-give
哦，我不喜欢那封信K因为那是
oh I don't like that letter K cuz that's
还有Krylov所以我该怎么说J所以我
also Krylov so what shall I say J so I
有J矢量z'原始BaBa
have J vector z' the original B a B a
将B平方组合起来
squared B up to that so combinations
给Krylov空间说它会命名
give the Krylov space say it will name
在哭泣之后，我们需要我们
it after crying off and we need we need
下标J表示它有多大
a subscript J to show how big it is it's
因此，这将是一个想法
dimension so so that will be the idea
让我完成这个想法的想法
well let me complete the idea the idea
将是如此组合所以这是一个
will be so there combination so that's a
空间的子空间蛮大的，如果我们做，如果
space a subspace pretty big if we do if
J是很大的，我要去看看了
J is big and I'm going to look for the
在那个空间的最佳解决方案，所以我要去
best solution in that space so I'm going
我不打算解决等于B的斧头
to I'm not going to solve ax equal B
我确切地想找到最好的解决方案
exactly I'm gonna find the best solution
最接近的解是最小二乘法
the closest solution the least square
在这个Krylov空间的解决方案我会
solution in this Krylov space I'm gonna
让J变大，所以这个空间有
let J be pretty big so this space has
有很多载体我有一个
got plenty of vectors in it I have a
这个空间的基础是我和一些人
basis for this space what I and some
这些基础向量的组合将
combination of these basis vectors will
是我的XJ所以我再次XJ将是最好的
be my X J so I again XJ will be the best
矢量或最接近的矢量最接近的
vector or the closest vector the closest
矢量在这个Krylov空间KJ的赌注
vector in this Krylov space KJ the bet
将是该领域的最佳载体
will be the best vector in that space
最近的一个，所以我知道空间是什么
the closest one so I know what the space
我把尺寸缩小到了J.
is I've reduced the dimension down to J
我可以找到这个最佳的因素还有的
and I can find this best factor there's
只有一个捕获，它是相同的捕获
just one catch and it's the same catch
我们的目标是帮助克格施密特
that gram-schmidt we're aiming to help
删除这是我的基础
to to remove that is this basis that I'm
现在我和所有人一起工作
right now I'm working with all
这些家伙和那些人的组合
combinations of these guys and those
可能是非常非常依赖可能
could be very very dependent that might
随时随地成为一个糟糕的基础
be a terrible basis anytime you wanted
至
to
重大计算是什么样的基础
big computations what kind of a basis do
你想要是的，那么基础是什么
you want yes so what sort of a basis is
很高兴找到投资找到
good to find to project on to to find
该子空间内的最佳解决方案
the best solution within that subspace
所以你有点想要投射
so you're sort of finding a projection
而且你已经拥有了矢量
and you've got you've got vectors that
跨越空间让你知道你是什么
span the space so you know what you're
投射到那些矢量可能
projecting on to but those vectors might
不是他们可能几乎依赖
not be they might be nearly dependent
他们可能都指向了几乎
they might all be pointing almost the
同样的方向你的情况
same direction in which case your
计算很可怕所以你呢
calculations are terrible so what do you
做正确的，然后是正确的
do orthe orthogonalize right and that's
我们的nolde进来的地方就在那里
where our nolde comes in and there's
也是一个名叫LAN的匈牙利人
also a Hungarian guy named LAN shows so
他们贡献的是如何做到的
that's what they contribute is how to
将该基础正交化然后一次
orthogonalize that basis and then once
你做到了
you've done that you
有一个正交的基础，当然
have an orthogonal basis and of course
正交基础是完美的做法
an orthogonal basis is perfect to do a
投影你看到每个人都必须这样做
projection do you see everybody has to
知道为什么这是正交基础
know that why is an orthogonal basis so
伟大的正统甚至让我们只是
great orthonormal even let's just
记得假设我有一个向量X它
remember suppose I have a vector X it's
这里不知道，但假设我想我
unknown here but suppose I suppose I
有它，我想将它写为我们
have it and I want to write it as our
这些正统人员的组合如此
combination of these orthonormal guys so
你说是啊是什么样的
you say yeah what is it about
正交Q的，使这个容易
orthonormal Q's that makes this easy to
做它不会与a
do which it would not be with a
任意的基础，所以这是真的
arbitrary basis so this this is really
可爱我看到这个向量的Q倍
cute I'm see right Q times this vector
C'S列的Q的Q的是在
of C's column the Q the Q's are in the
Q的列是C的，我们乘以a
columns of Q the C's we're multiplying a
矩阵由一个矢量，这是好的
matrix by a vector that's just okay it's
列的组合是什么
a combination of the columns that's what
我们得到了什么是什么时候
we get and what's the point of when
当Q是正交的时候
these when the Q's are orthogonal
我们能得到答案的答案是什么？
what's the answer we can get the answer
马上所以我们在这里我们试图
straight away so we here we're trying to
我们试图找到系数
we're trying to find the coefficients
关于a的基矢量Q.
with respect to the basis vectors Q of a
给出向量X，答案是什么
given vector X and what's the answer to
这一问题的点通常是
that question the point is usually to
找到它们必须的系数
find their coefficients C would have to
是Q逆X我们必须解决这个问题
be Q inverse X we'd have to solve that
我们必须解决的方程组
system of equations we do have to solve
那个方程组但是什么
that system of equations but what
哪里是收益或思想
where's the payoff from or thought
whoresonnormalbasisqinverse是Q.
whoreson normal basis q inverse is Q
转移那是收益，所以它是
transpose that's the payoff so it's
告诉我
telling me
那找到c1我怎么找到c1这个
that to find c1 how do I find c1 this
这说是先进行q1转置
this says take the first q1 transpose
用X，我会在这里说同样的话
with X that I'll say the same thing here
把第一个组件作为第一个组件
take the first component the first
向量与X的关系将是关于c1Q1
vector with X that'll be about c1 Q 1
转置Q1我只是拿点
transpose Q 1 I'm just taking the dot
Q1和Q的一切产品
product of everything there with Q 1 and
然后是C2Q1转置Q2，依此类推
then a C 2 Q 1 transpose Q 2 and so on
但有什么好再告诉我的
but what's good it tell me again the
这些都是0，Q1转置Q.
these are all 0 and the Q 1 transpose Q
1是1所以它是完美的C1是Q1
1 is 1 so it's perfect C 1 is Q 1
转置X，这就是那个
transpose X and that's exactly what that
告诉我们的第一个组件是
tells us the first component is the
第一行Q转置，即Q1
first row of Q transpose which is Q 1
转换X是的，所以这是主意
transpose with X yeah so that's the idea
所以这就是这个想法在这里
so that's the idea here
这就是我们的nolde和lan的原因
that's the reason for our nolde and lan
显示出名的是他们的想法
shows being famous is that they figured
找出正交化的好方法
out a good way to orthogonalize that
基础是啊是啊我们想看看是什么
basis yeah yeah do we want to see what
他们做了或只是那些将在
they did or just those would be in the
注意到它是如何做到这一点的
notes it's a well how do you do it so
这是我们不好的基础
this is the basis this is our not good
基础，然后我们的良好基础正在进行
basis and then our good basis is going
要Q，所以我会把B作为Q1的意思
to be Q's so I'll take B to be Q 1 will
什么是正确的选择
be what what would be the right choice
对于Q1井，我将采用第一个向量
for Q 1 well I'll take the first vector
并规范它，但它只是我们只是
and normalize it but it just we're just
这样做的施密特会是什么Q的
doing gram-schmidt what would q to be
我怎么能找到Q2
how would I find Q 2 following the
克施密特的想法
gram-schmidt idea
我将BI减去其组件
I take a B I subtract off its component
在这个q1方向，我正常化和
in this q1 direction and I normalize and
他们都没有Leland显示算法
all they are no Leland shows algorithm
就是那个克-施密特的想法
is is that same gram-schmidt idea
应用于这些Krylov载体也是如此
applied to these Krylov vectors so so so
我们都知道土地表演没有租约
are know the land shows are no lease for
a的任何矩阵和LAN选择
any matrix and LAN choices for a
对称矩阵，你得到一些
symmetric matrix where you get some
特别的好处所以他们所做的只是
special benefit so what they did is just
你现在可以说他们刚刚写下来了
you could say now they just wrote down
事实上，克施密特可能上涨了
gram-schmidt in fact probably up the
标准克施密特，因为我们这是
standard gram-schmidt because we this is
我们真的不想要的情况
a case where we really don't want to
交换列
exchange columns
我不想突然被推入
I don't want suddenly to be pushed into
这个我宁愿把它们整理好
this one I'd rather take them in order
因为它恰好是正确的
because it just turns out right and that
这是在说明中，让我告诉你
that this is in the note so let me tell
你在哪里这将是部分
you where this is this would be section
2.1所以这本书的第二部分是
2.1 so part two of the book which is
我们在哪里，第一部分如此
where we are and the first section so
什么是一起在这里
what is what all together is in this
第一节，当你看它
first section when you look at it that
截面是标准数值线性
section is standard numerical linear
代数什么课程和麻省理工学院
algebra what any course in and MIT
提供18.3我不确定数字
offers 18.3 i'm not sure of the number
330也许这就是所有的事情
330 maybe which is all all things like
这个Krylov会有没有他们
this Krylov would be there are no they
土地显示当然克和施密特
land shows of course gram and schmidt
将有这五个人谁已经
would be there that's five people who've
想到了同样的事情
thought of the same thing
所以第2-1节总结了什么
and so that section 2-1 summarizes what
什么是非常好的很多教科书
what's in really good a lot of textbooks
让我提一下最喜欢的一本书
and let me mention a favorite a book by
教授和弓
professor and and bow
或者圣经所以这可能是片刻
or the Bible so this is maybe a moment
告诉你关于两本书的两本书
to tell you about two two books on
经典数值线性代数是什么
classical numerical linear algebra what
你做的是一千个订单的矩阵
you do for matrices of order a thousand
不是为了数百万的矩阵
not for matrices of order millions
这就是你必须重新思考这样
that's that you have to rethink so
奖杯和弓不被称为数字
trophies and bow isn't called numerical
线性代数，你知道吗？
linear algebra and do you know the
数字圣经的作者
authors of the Bible of of numerical
线性代数，这是一本教科书和
linear algebra so that's a textbook and
什么我下来我们要去现在写下来
what I'm down we're gonna write down now
最后是750页，它已经成长为
finally is 750 pages it's grown to in in
它的第四版是圣经
its fourth edition it's the Bible for
所有数值线性代数人和
all numerical linear algebra people and
它是由golem和vanloan编写的
it's written by golem and van loans so
基因Golub是一个了不起的人
gene Golub was a remarkable guy he
可能写的不多于约
probably didn't write more than about
11页这查理写道最
eleven pages of this Charley wrote most
但是golem是一个了不起的人
of it but golem was a amazing person who
走遍世界，联系人民
traveled the world and connected people
留下要写的论文和
and left behind papers to be written and
和书籍被写入，因此，这
and books to be written and so that this
加利班贷款现在排在第四位
ghaliban loan is now in the fourth
音量和它有很多好东西和
volume and it has so much good stuff and
引用它就像是好的
references that it's like the good
参考，这是很好的教科书
reference and this is the good textbook
如果你打算上课
if you were going to teach a course on
我认为数值线性代数
numerical linear algebra so I think
那是我已经达到了目的
that's I've come to the point to to
完成所以我真的已经完成了
finish so I'm really have finished along
带来额外的吸引力
with the extra attraction of the of this
不同的问题我用斧头完成
different problem I finished with ax
等于B，至少我现在是我
equal B and well at least I'm now I now
move on to what to do with really
继续前进到真正做什么
非常大的矩阵
really large matrices